[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-
radio.net SC radio is brought to you by
the it computer society and by It
software Magazine online at computer.org
[Music]
software workos is a modern identity
platform built for B2B SAS it provides
easy to use apis for authentication user
identity and complex Enterprise features
like SSO and skim provisioning workos is
a drop-in replacement for azero and
supports up to 1 million monthly active
users for free it's perfect for B2B SAS
companies frustrated with high costs
opaque pricing and lack of Enterprise
capabilities supported by Legacy off
vendors today hundreds of high growth
scale-ups use work OS including ones you
probably know like versel webflow and
Loom check out work os.com sadio to
learn
more
hi all welcome to this episode of
software engineering radio this is your
host kin shangi and today we welcome
rishy say Rishi has been a platform
architect at Apple a co-founder and CTO
at harness.io which is a cicd platform
and he is now founder and CEO at
cn. today we will explore the technology
and methodology behind how sapen
leverages gen to help developers
automate testcode generation rich is
there anything else you'd like to add to
your bio before we get started hey kin
thank you so much for inviting me great
to be here I think really covered it
well other than cpti you know the
harness at iio and you know my at Apple
one thing that I can add it is you know
I'm really really passionate about the
developers tooling you know that
anything that leads to help the
developer become more productive so
before founding the cpti I was more into
the software delivery space you know
with the cpti this is a bit in the
Upstream environment you know especially
for the developers you know so that they
don't get stuck in the testing process
so yeah I'd love to you know discuss
more before we get into the first set of
questions I'd like to point our
listeners to episode 167 which is the
history of junit and the future of
testing with kenak which I think sets a
good stage or how we're going to change
some of those
methodologies yeah well while the
methodology changes the problems that
need to be solved are probably the same
you know starting with identifying what
to test and input can you comment on
that and maybe help us understand all
the things a tester needs to solve or
the developer needs to solve yeah that's
a great question you know the software
testing has been as old as is the
software itself right you know so ever
since you know started building the
product you know you needed something to
test it even the testing has itself
evolved with the software development
now so if you recall you know back in
days you know we used to have you know
the waterfall the software testing used
to be a very significant stage in this
entire software development life cycle
and you as you referenced about the canb
episode you know I had a chance to
listen to that episode you know before
this recording so you know if you see
you know the back in the early 2010 to
where we have come today the problem
statement Remains the Same that you know
we want to assess the quality of our
product we want to make sure the product
that we deliver you know it's meeting
the requirement and you know it's
helping you know the customers all their
users to have a good experience but the
software development landscape itself is
changed I think the way we are building
the software the way we are de you know
the delivering the software that itself
has changed and if you dig deeper
underlying the requirement exactly the
same thing broadly speaking almost every
product will have some functional
testing requirement you know we'll have
some kind of non-functional testing
requirement and then you know you can
just break it down into this multiple
areas you you start tackling you know
each one of them in a respective way and
you solve it so it's really right
observation that the requirement itself
is same but it's just the way we tackle
has changed in addition to identifying
the functional requirements and hence
what needs to be tested to meet them
things keep changing all the time so
identifying what has changed and how to
test the Delta is another problem that
one probably has to focus on yes yes so
back in days you know we used to have a
testing done by a QA team you know
everything was manual and that evolved
as you know sort of test automation so
you're not only just doing the testing
one time but you're writing a program to
simulate the entire process all set the
steps so that you can test as many times
and now the test automation itself is
getting replaced by some kind of
automated process of the test automation
is generated right so the underlying
philosophy that most of this Q engineer
used to follow is you know what we call
it as a test pyramid right so you know
whatever the testing requirement that
you had you know you just break it down
otherwise it becomes quite overwhelming
so I'll give you an example let's say we
have a web application you know there is
some sort of authentication layer in the
front and then you have the actual web
application doing it you know imagine
that it's a broker application you know
it might have a you know let's say
thousands of different use cases or you
know the thousands of different test
cases that are emerging out of it but
then you have some kind of
authentication that can vary you know
you might have the Google based
authentication you might do OCTA based
authentication or it may be you know
traditional you know the user ID and the
password kind of authentication but the
way a senior Q engineer will do it is
that they will take these two things in
a two layers of the application and test
it independently and so you have a three
mode of authentication but then you
don't do three times hundreds of these
test cases you know that becomes 300
instead you do three testing of these
authentication separately and you do
this 100 test cases separately and so
it's just total 103 so that is one
example right it is the same philosophy
that you know the most of the QA
engineer will follow they will break
down the overall testing requirement in
the form of what we call it unit testing
where you just go and focus on this
individual the test you know the test
classes individual methods you know
let's make sure each and every methods
are behaving the way it's supposed to
behave you know they will do you know
sort of integration testing just try to
identify those different logical layers
within the code or your application and
making sure these are all coming
together it's all you know the coming
along and then you know the finally
those end to endend testing you know
some of the flows you want to make sure
as a user you know when they are using
the application you know all of them are
coming together and it's all performing
so those are like you know very high
level you just break it down those
functional testing requirement and then
you try to tackle one by one you employ
you know the certain strategies so that
there is not a massive sprawl of the
test cases or you know the test code
because everything that you do
eventually has to be maintained and so
you know a senior in know the engineer
you know they are always looking to
optimize everything optimize the number
of unit test cases optimize number of
the integration test cases and the end
in test cases you might have come across
you might see some of the engineers you
know they will be very creative about
introducing the right input data for
these test cases so that it goes and
touches as many different code blocks
you know it touches as many different
test cases so the overall number of the
amount of the code which accumulates in
the code base is minimal and you know
that in the end you know it helps you to
minimize the overall the cloud
expenditure you know it helps you
minimize the overall the test code
liability because in theend everything
has to be maintained and I guess happy
path and also failure cases have a lot
of benefit to make sure they're working
and expected it is you know and I think
this is where you know not to
underestimate like the software
developers I think the software
developers they come from the sort of
mindset you know they're always good at
you know the building and amazing the
design and architecture but more like
the traditional QA individuals they come
with a different mindset they look at
the product spec they look at the code
and they always have you know this
paranoid kind of mindset that you know
you're always looking at what are the
different loopholes you know how this
application could potentially fail in
the real production environment and so
that is the reason why you know the
software desting becomes so overwhelming
it's a very simple code like you know
five lines 10 lines of the code but if
you look at like the number of the test
cases that are emerging out of it can be
exponential the moment you have there's
something called you know the cyclomatic
complexity and so cyclomatic complexity
is one of the way to measure the code
every time when you introduce some kind
of conditional statements or you know a
kind of loop it will
automatically lead to you know the two
different parts and so a simple code
just you know the five lines 10 lines of
the code you know might have two or
three the conditional or the for Loop
while loop kind of statements you know
will automatically lead to you know 10
you know the 20 different test cases and
you know that is the reason why there
are so many the test code you know so
much test code has to be written and I
think this is where the QA engineer they
are really really good they always focus
on the test cases that are more
meaningful they capture the posi POS
test cases but they also capture this
negative test cases in such a way the
amount of the code doesn't accumulate
too much and it remains within the realm
of mainis today of course we are talking
about how to help
engineering with this by automating a
lot of the test so there's a lot of
problems that have to be solved 100 can
you give us some history around what has
been happening in this area of automated
test generation yeah so you know when
you're talking about the test code or
the test automation there are two things
involved there's one which is the
planning and strategy aspect of it and
in the back in days you know most of the
Q Engineers used to look at the business
requirement document or the product
specification they would come up some of
the plan you know these are the
different test cases that have to be
executed and have to be done in order to
certify certain product and then there
is an actual implementation that once
you identify you know the set of test
cases then somebody has to write the
code to automate the entire testing
process so we have you know again there
has been many attempts historically
obviously there is not a good way of
understanding the product specification
that come up with this numero test cases
that is always done manually I think you
know that is also changing with the
recent evolution of the AI you know with
the with our comfortable understand the
product in product specification and tie
you know the certain action with it
there is an implementation aspect you
know how to gener the toast code you
know that has gone through the many
attempts you know you might have heard
of something called the random testing
or the input fuzzing you know the back
in days a lot of people would write you
know the code trying to know it is like
a code that is trying to understand the
code you know trying to understand each
and every instruction and trying with
this various inputs and just watching
observing you know where exactly it ends
like what are the different code blocks
that are getting executed with those
those random testing and foring but
again you know it's it was not a very
viable solution I don't think you know
it took where we would have liked
because there number of combinations
that you can expect uh will be too many
and it's just impossible to use some
random testing even with the best of the
heris stics that you can expect you it's
just not possible to cover all the test
Cas scenarios and and come up with a
good results then there are something
called you know the symbolic execution
there is you know the model based
testing so again all of them are were
geared towards the fact that you know
let's try to understand the code try to
build a form of you know the equation
try to figure out you know what is the
right value of the input that I could
potentially pass it which will steer
through this different execution path
and potentially give me the result that
covers everything in the code and so in
some way you know we are able to
generate the test code and provide the
right set of the input data so that it
covers the test cases this problem in
computer science you know it's known as
you know satisfiability modular Theory
you know it is one of these NP hard
problem you know in a computer science
you know something which is not easily
solvable in the finite times or you know
in other words you it becomes infinitely
complex to solve this kind of problem so
that was the case now obviously things
have changed those were the attempts it
did something it did solve in the some
scenarios you know those Solutions are
still used in some cases where you are
doing the in the security testing where
you're trying to figure out if there is
a one potential input that could
potentially crash the system or you know
bring stack over flow or you know some
of these kind of you know the issues but
it hasn't made as much Headway on the
functional testing you know the most of
the functional testing is still done by
the individuals either by the QA tester
or the developers you know they are the
ones who are analyzing coming up with
the various test cases and they are the
ones who are writing the code to test it
you mentioned fast testing I'd like to
point our listeners to episode
474 Paul Butcher on F
testing your point is that use of this
technique has not worked for functional
testing given it has the same level of
complexity as I think you mention
symbolic execution which examines the
programs by identifying which input
result in activating which parts of the
code and then you also talked about
model testing can you elaborate a little
bit more on what was the approach there
and possibly why that was not successful
yeah it's a strongly tied with our older
approach of the waterfall model of the
software development and so if you go
back 10 20 years ago the entire industry
was big on creating the uml diagram
coming up with the right design sign and
then you start writing the code this
whole extensive process doesn't work you
know so it's a very similar kind of
approach on this model based testing
where you try to create this model and
then try to use that model as a base to
generate the code in automated fashion
so now these approaches don't work in
more modern in the fast-paced kind of
environment you know everything is
changing so fast and you don't just
create a model and you end up
maintaining one more thing especially if
you're making the change every day you
know you're deing the code every day
maybe multiple times in a day it doesn't
work so again it's a pretty the heavy
process that was there and that didn't
gain enough traction because it's so
hard to implement I see so you also
mentioned analysis of the code
complexity any pointers on how that was
leveraged in the past for automated test
generation yeah there are you know the
cyclomatic code complexity which really
deals with what are the different
execution path potentially you can have
based on the input and there are a lot
of the static code analysis tool you
know it can look into the program it can
understand the various instructions and
then it can come up with those different
test cases that are applicable so the
way it happens is that you know if let's
say if you have a simple program trying
to calculate a factorial let's say
and you know you have written a you know
method like if uh input x equal to zero
return this if input x equals something
else then you know get the factorial x -
one times the value X and so on so again
you know this is a simple if then else
condition you know it could be for Loop
and while loop and so you know every
condition adds into the overall you know
the complexity and you know that is used
to come up with the list of the
execution parts that are applicable in
the code and that's how people end up
creating the test out of it on the other
hand the biggest challenge remains is
what is the right input that you can
introduce which will lead to those
different execution path and that has
the same level of problem and so it's a
similar kind of problem that the input
fuzzing or the symbolic execution had
just suffered you know it's not easy you
cannot come up with the value especially
if the code is extremely complex sounds
like model based test
has its place in certain approaches to
software development and lexical
approaches also have some level of
success but none of them have really
solved the larger problem and now we are
coming to the use of generative AI can
you discuss that like what are the
capabilities today that large language
models offer for use of TCO generation
yeah yeah 100% so I think the approach
itself is very different I think in the
backend days you when we were trying to
generate the code we were always trying
to interpret the individual instruction
in the code and then we trying to do it
you know in this particular case now the
generative Ai and especially for the
code it's nothing but an extension of
the recent breakthroughs that we have
seen in the large language model and the
natural language processing right and so
you know the chat GPT or in the Google
board or in the Google Pam 2 or the Lama
coding almost all of them are you know
the based on the same thing and so here
know we are using this deep learning
algorithm and the large neural network
to train the huge amount of the data set
and then you know those examples which
were created by the humans become a base
for these models to you know to provide
you some output or help you you know
doing the code generation or even the
test code generation so it's approach
itself is different you know it's unlike
the typical algorithm mic approach here
you have a program that is understanding
the natural language processing it's
looking at the examples from you know
the GitHub where you have a lot of
public repository there is a lot of code
available for every code and you have
some sort of test code available you
know it's discovering the internet and
you know various developers Community
forums and looking at many examples you
know how people have written the code
and you know how the code is tested and
based on that it's a suggesting
something right so here the approach is
completely different you know not
necessarily taking the algorithmic
approach instead you know it's a
learning and based on that it's
providing the feedback for you know the
test program right which is very very
different I think you know it's a very
successful just like the charp just like
in the world of the natural language
processing it's much better on the you
know the code generation side but again
you know it has a long way to go love to
share more details there are some
shortcomings as of now but this approach
has taken much farther than anything
that we had in the past can you tell us
any example or any story that you may
have about when you actually used an AI
generated test directly what happened
did it work as expected or did not work
yeah yeah so I think there are the
plenty of examples you know in fact I'm
sure like you know you are aware of this
whole Buzz about the generative AI you
know anything which is fairly common or
which is available in the public domain
I think generative AI is awesome and so
let's say you know if I'm trying to look
to write a program called email
validation and if I just give a simple
prompt you know my the generative AI
will easily generate the code for the
email validation let say if I have the
email validation code and I'm asking the
Genera AI to generate a test code out of
it it will do it right away there is no
problem I W say like in the problem the
limitation with the generate API
encounters is when you have really
complex your own project your own code
you know which has nothing to do with
this any of this public repository or
the public the simple example you know
it has nothing to do with one of the
sample code that you might have come
across either on the GitHub or maybe
internet forums or you know maybe in one
of the schools or university you know
writing the quick sort algorithm or the
mot or any of these things then the
generative AI does run into the
limitation and especially when you have
like you know 50 lines 100 lines or even
much longer the code which is very very
common in the real world environments at
many of the Enterprises and I think this
is where you know I have seen the
generative AI does the partial work you
know I won't say it don't do anything
you know it will do the partial work
where you it will create some skeleton
or it will do something it will write
something and expect the software
developers to take up from there try to
understand what it has done and try to
complete the rest of them so I have seen
the varying result in some of the
scenarios where you know I've seen the
Genera way I just created a skeleton
didn't do anything you know I've seen
example where it wrote some code which
was completely unrelated and there are
times where it has done a really good
job where like 80% or 90% part of the
job but you know I as a developer since
I understand the code I could easily
complete remaining 10 to 20% and get the
job done in that case what would you say
about the productive it using gen as
compared to the programmers starting
from scratch themselves yeah I think the
number one thing is that there is a
increase in the productivity you know no
matter where you start like if you're
starting from the scratch you know you
with a simple prompt you know definitely
you gain a lot of code if you're doing
something you know an existing code then
you do some help from the generative AI
so again you know I would like to call
this you know the moment when I'm
talking about this generative AI it's a
typical the Cod generation that us see
read from the chat GPT or maybe in
Google p to or in theod but then there
has been many companies that they build
the product on top of it and so they
have done you know some wonderful job on
top of you know the current state of the
genni and we have done a better job you
the sap is one of them so for example if
a developer is writing the code in an
existing you know the code base Genera
can help to some extent but the
developers still have to put a
significant effort understanding the
changes that they're doing and you know
coming from the testing perspective like
the developers still have to figure out
what are the new set of you know the
test cases that are emerging out of the
changes and the test cases that are
becoming obsolete you know so there is
the good amount of the work that is
still left over with the individual
developers and I think that's where
instead of you know using the plain gen
AI from the CH GPT or you know any of
these tools I think probably the tools
like the Sapient AI is better because it
has built on top of it we have to train
the gni to be more accurate than that
and then you know we have also created
some kind of experience on top of that
so that I just developer they don't have
to figure out themselves instead of the
solution itself reveal the set of the
changes that has to be brought up can
you talk a little bit about the
methodology of training the Gen yes so
there are the Gen tool or you know the
models that are available and basically
you know these models can be
instantiated and then it can be trained
with you know your own set of data and
so you know we have gone through this
like you know years of this whole
experience where you know we have seen
we have built a layer on top of it which
is continuously verifying you know the
output from the Gen
and so you know gen is very notorious
that you know it might hallucinate you
know it can give The Confident response
even if the response is not necessarily
accurate and you know it happens the
same thing on the coding side where you
know there is a certain code that gets
generated but it's not accurate so we
have used like some of the programs to
look at the code interpret the code in
an automated way making sure is it a
right code it's not a right code if it's
not right code then we try with this
various mechanism we have built some of
this our own internal Secret Sauce where
we look at the code you know we break it
down in this multiple chunks and you
know send it back to the generative AI
so that the overall accuracy is much
higher that is one and then we take it
to the even next level where once we
learn the certain pattern about the
generative AI you know where it's not
performing well we introduce the right
set of training data so that the
generative ai's response is more
accurate training data and you said you
know many years worth of code and you
also mentioned that the rappers if Inc
correct me if I'm the wrong terminology
but the rappers check the code that is
generated and maybe
retry can you talk a little bit about
what that check
entails yes so let's say like more from
the you know the testing perspective you
know let's say you have a certain code
that code leads to you know 10 different
use cases and so so there is a layer
that will try this various use cases try
with the Gen look at the output from the
code it will make sure it is addressing
the use case that you had intended for
if it's not then you know it will make
certain changes you know it will break
the original code into this multiple CHS
and you know it will try to you know
reprompt the jni so that it gets a
different output so there is a sort of
the flows that we have created
internally and and that makes the
overall code the final output of the
code for the individual developers to be
more accurate and more relevant I see so
I was looking at sapien's website and it
looks like you've developed a plugin for
the IDE M and as you kind of explained
it does use gen to generate the unit
test but it analyzes the results and I
also read it comprehends exit points of
methods Etc how does it do that like
what is the learning there is that
algorithmic or is that also AI based
yeah it's it's about algorithmic as well
as the AI but you mentioned the
important point about this plugins I
think I just cannot emphasize more that
probably the IDE plugin is the most
natural place for the software
developers to interact I have seen most
of the software developers they don't
even come out of this intellig you know
the vs code I think these plugins are
are extremely powerful you can get in
know all sort of environment including
the terminal many of these utility these
are all built into the ID and that is
the reason why I think you know I'm
really really big on the you know the
plugins because that's the place for the
aut developers to go now how do we do it
I think the plug-in has a lot of
Advantage so number one you know it
helps us create this whole simulation
richer experience because the plugin has
the access to the entire project so we
have a much deeper
understanding about the source code you
know it's a necessary the dependencies
and so on so no one has to manually feed
the code or to provide any kind of
context Instead This plug-in is able to
extract all the details all the
information so that you know we can help
our developers there once we have that
information then you know it does go
through the both like you know
algorithmic as well as this AI approach
you know it works in conjunction it
integrates with some of the back end and
then combination of these two are able
to generate the test can you elaborate
it connects with the back end what do
you mean yeah I think when it's a back
end it's really the cloud environment
and so you know let's say if I as a
developer you know if I'm working on the
certain code if I'm making certain
changes now I'm about to generate the
test code this plugin is capable of
pulling the necessary details and then
it will integrate the cloudbased Zend AI
back end to help generate the code use
the the generative Ai and so like you
know the generative AI is like you know
very you know the complex process
obviously we cannot run everything on
the plugin the plugin is really like you
know an interface for the individual
developers to work but you know the lot
of things are done in the back end in
the in the SE cloud in terms of the
languages that you support is that
simply depends on how much training is
available in that language for J I like
what language do you support today and
maybe you can talk about why it's that
set yes yes so the Gen you know again
the plain vanilla gen you know which is
available from the Google from the open
a many of them and you know you could
could just use it you know anyone can
build a raer and those languages can be
supported from the day I think what I'm
really big on is the fact that this SP
geni is not sufficient for the
individual developers because the open
has published one do not open like the
Microsoft co-pilot the GitHub co-pilot
published one report where they admitted
that the 29% of the code that gets
generated from the co-pilot doesn't
require any kind of involvement from the
developers but the remaining 71% is
where the developers they have to first
understand what is the code that has
been generated and then they have to
work on top of the and I think this is
where we have to be careful that let's
not just uh
use the code directly generated from in
the large language model because then
you know we are not adding enough value
and I think you know what were the
languages that we support we have been
building the layer on top of it and so
that the accuracy level is not at 29%
but accuracy level is probably you know
80% and so the individual developers
have to step in only 10 to
20% instead of like 70 to 80% right now
the CPN supports any of the jdk language
family the Java you know the cotl and so
on we are expanding our reach into the
other languages the python is on our
road map and we should be you know
publishing or releasing that pretty soon
and there is a goang there is a
typescript you know some of these
languages are out there as well in our
road map but again the goal is it's not
just about just supporting the language
but supporting in a way that we bring
enough value and make sure the
individual developers have a very
minimal effort required to get the job
done in terms of training is it training
with just the code or it's also training
with test cases it's both the training
with the code and the training with the
test cases so given a product
specification you want to understand
about all the test cases that are
applicable for it and so there are a lot
of acceptance test cases that get
generated out of it but once individual
developers are implementing the code
then the code itself gets interpreted by
the Gen and you know we are able to
generate the test code out of it the
reason I'm asking that even for just
somebody directly using chat GPT apis or
chat gbd interface for example will
their accuracy improve if they present
examples of test cases in the prompt is
another approach maybe starting with
writing some skeletal test cases and
asking the Gen to improve them do you
think that has a higher success
definitely it will get better than you
know what you get it in the first
attempt but again you know it's an
ongoing effort like you know it really
like coming across the different uge
cases where the gni has not been giving
you the good result know this is where
like we have got this bread and butter
this is what we do we figur out the
different scenarios where the Gen has
not been working well and we are giving
the different prompt we are giving the
different training data to make sure the
output is better can you give some
examples of numbers like how many tests
would get generated based on a certain
body of code and how does that
correspond to the pyramid that you
talked about earlier yeah so it depends
on the code that has been written and
how well it has been written what we
have seen in our experience that if the
functional you know whatever the the
number number of lines of the code that
you have it for the production your test
code ends up becoming somewhere around 2
to 10 times that many lines of the code
this is an average number but it really
depends on like how the code has been
written if the cyclomatic complexity is
high that means the ratio is going to be
higher if it's a really really a simple
code then it might be just the same
number of lines of the code can you just
clarify my understanding so the number
of test cases generated like you said is
much higher if the code is more complex
has many code paths is that also how the
parameters that you use to validate once
the tests are generated for example if
you expect it based on the code
complexity n number of tests to be
generated but you only see you know much
fewer is that when you reprompt and
retry is that the kind of enhancements
that you were alluding to that have been
implemented I I think the number of test
cases is still predictable you can ask
the Gen to do it or you may not want to
do it I think what I was alluding to is
the actual code that is generated by the
Gen so imagine that you have the test
code that has a certain value like input
and that doesn't work and so you what
about the code that you came up with and
you try to execute an environment but it
failed and so the code that was
generated you know ideally it was
supposed to work but it didn't work and
there as we dig deeper into it we
figured out there are some scenarios
there are the certain methods there are
combination of things that have been
used where this gni has not been doing
well which means that let's try to
prepare some code and you know feed the
jni so that it has a better
understanding about these scenarios so
from that point onwards the code that is
generated with the input is all correct
and and it compiles it executes
successfully without any user
intervention as you're explaining this
I'm wondering how does uh tdd or test
driven development methodology fit in
with this approach or does it not at all
the tdd it is like you know one of the
thing that came in early 2010 when
everyone was really big on the extreme
programming and and so on so the T
doesn't fit in I think you in fact like
is won't fit in anywhere like you know
whereever the environment is really the
fast based kind of environment you where
things are continuously changing the TR
is something you know you create the
test and you try to build everything
around it the reality is when things are
really really flowed your test is
changing as well and so you don't get
this time however the tdd has two more
things that comes as a part of it and
obviously the tdd brings the quality in
the center stage that means whatever
that you ship it has to be of really
high quality and the second thing is it
forces the individuals to pick the right
design choices and so it's not just
about doing the code coverage it's also
about having the right design in the
code so that it remains testable you
know if things are not testable you
might be able to do the coverage but you
know it's just a matter of time it's so
brittle it will start failing in fairly
soon but the TD forces you because you
know test is the number one one thing
now with the tools like the seint AI you
are able to achieve the same thing now
you know you no longer have an excuse to
not cover the quality side from the
beginning and so anytime when you are
making the change and if you're shipping
any kind of functionality you try to
cover the quality right there and if you
have not written the code in a certain
way you get prompted about those
fundamental issues and you are able to
make those changes before it's to it so
it sounds like a lot of the focus that
you have is on unit testing uh is that
correct yes at the moment I think you
know our Focus has been more on the unit
testing again the goal is to help the
developers as much as possible ever
since this whole shift lift moment has
started the most of the QA
responsibility has converged with the
you know the software development
process but I still see you know the QA
team stepping in doing a lot of testing
integration testing they're doing a lot
of end to end testing but when it comes
to the unit testing That Remains the
sole responsibility of the individual
developers and that's one of the reason
why we wanted to focus more on the unit
testing but in long term our goal is to
really cover the entire the QA spectrum
and so as the shift lift movement has
been going on the software development
team has received like lot of
responsibility they are not just
implementing the code and building the
new features but also doing the QA
they're also involved in
operationalizing things and shipping the
code all the way into production
environment and I think this is where
those various tools and the platforms
will come in and so the developers they
don't necessarily be need to become a QA
engineer or the operational engineer
instead they can use these various
platforms simply push the button get the
job done and take care of the full
responsibility let's talk a little bit
now about how does the de developer
actually get comfortable about the
quality of the tests so do you measure
or have you measured or are you in the
process of measuring how effective the
tests are at finding bugs or regressions
as compared to you know hand-coded tests
yeah so the testing framework itself is
the challenging things I think the
testing framework itself is evolving I
think one way to to measure the testing
framework is how often the software
developers have to intervene to make the
software test pass and so any of the
tools that we are coming across and all
of this AI assisted tool these are not
perfect it's getting better but it's not
100% there and the code that it
generates or the number of the test
cases that it generates it's always
bringing the software developers into
the context so that they can review they
can verify before before they can commit
the changes so right now it's always
working as a co-pilot mode where
software developers are equally involved
in the entire process and always
verifying so I think the goal is that
these tools become so smart so
sophisticated so that the code generated
doesn't require any intervention from
the developers so that is number one
other than that I think really like in
the sh it's really the developers who
have to look into the code and verify
there is no no Silver Bullet that it
will automatically know everything
especially those semantic context about
the you know what is required from the
code is a bit hard to implement and it's
not there as a part of the AI so this
analysis by the developer also means
that they have to retain some of their
earlier methodologies and Frameworks so
just having an idea of a test spec would
still be important right measuring code
coverage would still be important it is
important and I think that's where they
can also be a bit strategic about you
know engaging with the tools which is a
bit agnostic which is aligned with
whatever they were doing so if you're
adopting a tool which is totally
disruptive you know if it's bringing
some kind of proprietary stuff then it
will be a challenge what I'm seeing
nowadays especially with the cpti we
have taken the approach that let's not
bring anything proprietary let's try to
complement everything that software
developers have been doing they try to
become a multiplier into everything the
software developers have been doing and
so instead of they writing the code we
write the code probably 90% or maybe in
95% and then instead of taking like 20
to 40% of their time maybe it will take
like 5% of your time and it will get
exactly the same result that the
individual developers would have done
themselves so unit test today and what's
your vision for the future yeah I think
sure is bright for sure it's really I
think you know generative AI has been
massive I can see at least in the short
term the geni is not going to replace
the developers instead you know it's
going to make software developers
probably 10 times maybe 100 times more
productive with the devops you know I
can clearly see the time to Market has
significantly reduced now with the AI
That's going to accelerate the entire
process which means there is a more
amount of the code there is a more
number of iteration there will be a lot
more activity
going on in this world of the Enterprise
development all of this is extremely
exciting and it's very very promising
provid it it's managed and executed
properly else it can result into really
a massive quality issue it can turn
everything into the ktic situation and I
think this is where I feel really really
excited that after harness.io now my
focus is more on the quality side and
with the companies like the cant AI
which is laser focused on the quality if
the company start employing the tool
like this then they will be better
prepared from the quality standpoint so
that they can deal with the situation
they can make their developers more
productive with all the eii tools but
they they can also cover the quality
angle can you comment on the plans or
what makes sense like fitting in with
the existing framework so for unit test
for Java for example I my guess is you
use the test conformed to the J unit
spec is that a fair assumption it is and
I think this is what I was referring to
earlier that the software developers can
assume that the AI is not really going
to replace things but AI is going to
complement and the companies like the
cint AI which is built on this AI
platform is going to complement and
so everything that it produces has to
tie back with the generic framework like
the junit or xunit or you know if you're
using the python then P unit and so on
and bring the value bring the code on
top of it and so it can be understood by
the individual developers and it feel
like complimented instead of trying to
replace in any sound form rishy is there
any topic today that you feel we should
cover in more detail or we haven't
touched upon yeah we talked a lot about
the testing and I think a lot of our
conventions remain into within the unit
testing thing we talked a lot about the
cyclomatic complexity and other things
you love to share my thought about this
API to end to end testing the reality is
that you the quality has to be tackled
as a whole people are making the changes
the QA standpoint or more from the
developer standpoint I would like to
optimize the Q responsibility as unit
testing integration testing and you know
an testing and so on just to optimize
the cloud resources optimize the
efficiency and so on but everything has
to be looked together for the end users
so that they get the maximum benefit
when everything is becoming so
fast-paced then how these things are
going to be covered more from the Epi
perspective from the inter interesting
perspective love to share the thought I
know in some other episodes or so
because that itself remains aary broad
topic thank you so much I think this was
a wonderful conversation how can people
contact you if they have any followup
questions yes I think we are available
at ww cn. you know anyone can contact
from there or you know they could also
reach out to us using the email address
contact cn. we also have some Community
Forum so I would encourage people to
join there and just watch out you know
they can also subscribe to some of the
blogs or the newsletters so yeah they
can stay connected with us and I'd love
to be there that's really good to know
just one fin thought just on you know
your your invitation to people to
contact and give feedback at sapn
what are you hearing from people that
are testing or using the test Generation
Now how much is it adding to their
productivity are you are you getting any
feedback and how are you using that to
improve the process so the people who
are using the product I think they are
seeing a lot of benefit I think there
you know I I come across two group of
people one group they are seeing the
huge productivity gain because they were
spending so much time writing the code
as I said like you know what were the
functional code that you write your test
code could be as much as like twice the
number of lines of the code or maybe up
to like you know eight to 10 times
depending on how comprehensive you want
to implement right so that's the one
group of people that I see there is a
second group of people who
were taking this entire thing in a
hopeless manner in the sense like they
were just not writing the test at all
they don't have a time there is a
continuous agile Sprint going on every
two weeks you know they will come back
back try to finish many of these task
and then we move on and and try to take
the new set of task so for them it has
been amazing I think they are super
excited that they were all passionate
about the quality but the reality is
that it's very hard to balance the speed
and the quality together and you know in
the today's world where you know
everyone is trying to deliver bow
everyone is trying to rush the features
into this production environment for
them the tool like this has been the
lifeline that's the kind of feedback
that we see thanks rishy this is very
informative it's rapidly evolving area
and it was great to hear your thoughts
and how you are improving and adding
more functionality over